Guide to the Herman Salinger Papers, 1909-1982
Duke University. University Archives
Herman Salinger papers 1909-1982
Duke University. University Archives
Salinger, Herman, 1905-
13.2 linear feet Extent: 8,000 Items
Herman Salinger was a professor of German and Comparative Literature at Duke from 1955-1974. Collection includes correspondence, course and curriculum materials, poetry and manuscripts, speeches, photographs, and other materials. Also includes documents dealing with Duke activities and people, course and teaching materials, writings, and records of the Arthur Schnitzler Research Association.
UA.29.02.0046
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Herman Salinger Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1963-1983.
Biographical Note
Herman Salinger grew up in St. Louis, MO. He received his B.A. from Princeton University, his M.A. from Stanford University and his Ph.D. from Yale University. He also undertook graduate studies at the University of Berlin and the University of Cologne. During World War II, he fought in Germany as a captain in the U.S. Air Force. After teaching at Princeton, the University of Wisconsin, the University of Kansas and Grinnell College, Salinger came to Duke in 1955 as a professor of German and Comparative Literature, serving as chair in both departments. He remained on the Duke faculty until his retirement in 1974. His 1963 book of poetry, A Sign is the Sword won the Roanoke-Chowan Poetry Award. He died in 1983.
Collection Overview
Collection includes correspondence, course and curriculum materials, poetry and manuscripts, speeches, photographs, and other materials. The correspondence includes personal letters, correspondence with former students and professional correspondence. Also includes documents dealing with Duke activities and people, course and teaching materials, writings, and records of the Arthur Schnitzler Research Association.
Subject Headings
Salinger, Herman, 1905-; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University. Dept. of Germanic Languages and Literature; Germany -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- North Carolina -- Durham; World War, 1939-1945 -- Correspondence; Arthur Schnitzler Research Association; Salinger family
Related Material
Kulski (Wladyslaw W.) Papers, 1933-1987
Duke University Archives
Vollmer (Clement) Papers, 1898-1983
Duke University Archives
Knight (Douglas M.) Records, 1949-1970
Duke University Archives
Biographical Reference Collection, 1972-2004
Duke University Archives
University Archives Photograph Collection, 1861-2006
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Personal Correspondence, 1957-1972 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence (Originally in Letter Box), 1940-1968 (Box 1)
  - Haskell Bloch Correspondence, 1954-1974 (Box 1)
  - Job Applicants, 1955-1972 (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence, A-Z (Box 1)
  - Wiegand, Hermann Correspondence, 1945-1954 (Box 1)
  - World War II Letters (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Signatures Incomplete or Illegible, 1946-1981 (Box 1)
  - Writings, Correspondence, 1962-1971 (Box 2)
  - Poems (Box 2)
  - Loose Verses (Box 2)
  - Samaiu (Box 2)
  - Verse, undated (Box 2)
  - A Tear is an Intellectual Thing (Box 2)
  - David Salinger Correspondence, 1947-1972 (Box 2)
  - Near Requiem for a Near Corpse and Time Recaptured (Box 2)
  - We Seek the Wheel (Box 2)
  - Morgenstem Review (Box 2)
  - Princeton Undergraduate Thesis, 1927 (Box 2)
  - Yale Dissertation, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Stanford Master's Thesis, 1928 (Box 2)
  - Salinger Academic Writings (Bound Volumes), undated (Box 2)
  - Kleist's Penthesila: Amazon or Bluestocking? (Box 2)
  - La Fontaine (Box 2)
  - Speeches (Box 2)
  - Concerning Kafka's 'A Country Doctor' (Box 2)
  - Poetry as a Means (Box 2)
  - Francis Jammes (Box 2)
  - On Translating Lyric Poetry (Box 2)
  - Art of the Novel (Address to Princeton Students, 1939); Artist and Society (T. Mann) (Box 2)
  - Prodigal Son (Box 2)
  - K. Krolow Poems, Correspondence, etc., 1967-1979 (Box 2)
  - Klopstock (Box 2)
  - Johnson Reprint Co. (Box 2)
  - Ludwig Uhland (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 2)
  - MLA Seminar, 1968 (Box 2)
  - UNC Visiting Professorship, 1978-1980 (Box 2)
  - Vita and Bibliography (Box 3)
  - Bound Letters, v. I-VII, 1923-1932 (Box 3)
  - World War II Correspondence, 1945 (Box 3)
  - Wiegand Correspondence, 1961-1975 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence with Writers, Artist A. Bloch and Others, 1947 (Box 3)
  - Old Family Letters, etc., 1909-1932 (Box 3)
  - Kraus Correspondence, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Stevens Correspondence, 1954 (Box 3)
  - Kaufmann Correspondence, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Shapiro and MacLeish Correspondence, 1937-1953 (Box 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1957-1980 (Box 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1953-1958 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence re: Kronow, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Freshman Year (Verse), 1923-1925 (Box 4)
  - Verse, 1925-1926 (Box 4)
  - Summer Vacation, 1926 (Box 4)
  - Verse, 1927-1961 (Box 4)
  - Verse, This House of Verses, 1960-1968 (Box 4)
  - Verse and Translations, 1969-1975 (Box 4)
  - Verse and Translations, 1975-1982 (Box 4)
  - Verse, 1977-1982 (Box 4)
  - Stifter, Brigitta, Translated by H. Salinger (Box 4)
  - Peter Henisch (Translated by H. Salinger?) (Box 4)
  - Verse, Sacred Play Things (Box 4)
  - South Atlantic Quarterly (Box 5)
  - Edens, President A. Hollis (Box 5)
  - Phi Beta Kappa (Box 5)
  - German 201 and 209 and 133 - Goethe, Lyrics, etc. (Box 5)
  - German 103: 19th Century (Box 5)
  - Grinnell - German A2 (Box 5)
  - Bibliographies (Box 5)
  - Grinnell (Box 5)
  - Department Records (Box 5)
  - Library Bibliography (Desirata) (Box 5)
  - Reserve Book Lists (Box 5)
  - German 201 (Box 5)
  - Student Papers Retained [May be restricted, check with staff] (Box 5)
  - Publications, 1958 (Box 5)
  - Krolow Volume - Introduction (Box 5)
  - Reviews (Box 5)
  - Schnitzler Association (IASRA), 1961-1969 (Box 5)
  - IASRA Associate Members (Box 5)
  - IASRA Former Members (Box 5)
  - Letters of Invitation (Box 5)
  - Institutional Members (Box 5)
  - Complete Membership List (Box 5)
  - Student Members (Box 5)
  - IASRA Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 5)
  - Active Members (Box 5)
  - Declined (Box 5)
  - IASRA Financial Information (Box 5)
  - IASRA Journal (Box 5)
  - IASRA Membership, 1966-1967 (Box 5)
  - Comp Lit Program (Box 5)
  - 20th Century German Verse (Box 5)
  - Stewart Gordon - Modern Austrian Literature (Box 5)
  - General Robert E. Lee Information (Box 5)
  - SAMLA - 1961-1962 (Box 5)
  - Yale University Correspondence (Box 5)
  - Inventory (Box 6)
  - Items Separated, circa 1985 (Box 6)
  - Lecture Note Cards (Box 6)
  - Addresses: I Write Just for Myself… (Box 6)
  - Addresses: Introduction for Ellis Arnall, circa 1952 (Box 6)
  - Addresses: The Three R's of Poetry (Box 6)
  - Addresses: Some general remarks about Undergraduate Writing Problems: Prose and Verse (Box 6)
  - Addresses: How to read a poem (Panel Discussion) (Box 6)
  - Addresses: Is Jesus Christ God? (Box 6)
  - Addresses: Realism in Germany: 1830-1885 (Box 6)
  - Addresses: 5th Century B.C.: End of Classical Greek Period (Box 6)
  - Addresses: Romancement and Advancement: Moon As a Lollipop (Box 6)
  - Talk and Poem on Christmas, circa 1950s (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Poems (Box 6)
  - Notes, Quotations, Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Public Lectures, Poems, etc. (Box 6)
  - Talks, Reviews, etc. (Box 6)
  - Why Austrian Literature? (Box 6)
  - Addresses - SAMLA - 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - Heine - The Child in the Mann (Box 6)
  - Poem, 1972 (Box 6)
  - Poems on Latin American Project, 1975 (Box 6)
  - Experience in Africa (diary) (Box 6)
  - Poems to be Copied (Box 6)
  - Magic Root - Poem (Box 6)
  - Poems, 1967 (Box 6)
  - Poems, Copy II, 1965-1967 (Box 6)
  - Poems, 1965-1972 (Box 6)
  - Poems, 1967-1970 (Box 6)
  - Unpublished Manuscript, 1977 (Box 6)
  - Lyrica Germanica (Box 6)
  - Poem Drafts/Sketches, undated (Box 6)
  - Books Abroad, Summer 1948 (Box 6)
  - Fantasy, No. 26, 1942 (Box 6)
  - Above Ground Review, Spring 1971 (Box 6)
  - German Lyric Final Exam, Germ 133 (Box 6)
  - The Nineteenth Century (Comp Lit 119, University of Washington) (Box 6)
  - Comp Lit C58: Romanticism (and Comp Lit Miscellaneous) (Box 6)
  - Comp Lit 203: Realism (Box 6)
  - Herman Hesse (Box 6)
  - Hesse: Demian (Box 6)
  - Manon Lescaut (Box 6)
  - Comp Lit 205 Introduction (Box 6)
  - Marcel Proust (Box 6)
  - R.M. Rilke (Box 6)
  - Kafka Parables - Salinger Essay (Box 6)
  - Kafka Course Materials (Box 6)
  - Rilke Papers (Box 6)
  - Weigand; Zauberberg (Box 6)
  - Krutch: Proust (Box 6)
  - Camus, Lorca and Hagerkirst (Box 6)
  - Mann - Goethe (Box 6)
  - Course Materials, I-J (Box 6)
  - Mallarme and Mysticism (Box 6)
  - Wedekind, Frank (Box 6)
  - Comp Lit 204: Realism and Symbolism - Materials (Box 6)
  - Emery George - 1972 - Krolow and Lit Review (Box 6)
  - Humboldt - Stilftung (Box 6)
  - Franco-German Relations - Comp Lit 7 - MLA (Box 6)
  - Emery George - Literary Review - Translations (Box 6)
  - Karl Krolow (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, Printed Matter, Photos, etc. (Box 6)
  - Correspondence with Writers and Princeton Administrators, 1935-1942 (Box 6)
  - Artists Editions Mailing Envelope from Italy, 1954 (Box 6)
  - Items Separated, 1971-1980 (Box 7)
  - Patriotic Plays, Grinnell College (Box 7)
  - Austrian Lit Program - Memos, Papers, 1973 (Box 7)
  - Comparative Literature Committee Minutes, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
  - Comparative Literature Program, 1970-1972 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence w/European Writers, Relatives, Immigrant Writers (Krolow), Translators, Students, 1955-1966 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1944-1980 (Box 7)
  - Lectures, Including Announcements, 1972 (Box 7)
  - Heine Lectures Notes (Box 7)
  - Heine Paper for MLA (Box 7)
  - Heine - Valkyren Paper and Correspondence w/Johns Hopkins (Box 7)
  - Fichte Schelling Lecture Notes (Box 7)
  - Correspondence Re: Publications, 1982-1983 (Box 7)
  - Assorted Poems (Box 7)
  - Personal - Poems (Box 7)
  - Verse (Beginnings, Final Jottings, Miscellaneous), 1963-1980 (Box 7)
  - Generation Gap Speech (Box 7)
  - Auerbach: Philologie der Weltliteratur, 1967 (Box 7)
  - Betts Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Bienkowsky Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Albert Bloch Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Haskell Bloch Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Felix Braun Paper, 1962 (Box 7)
  - Broch Correspondence, circa 1950 (Box 7)
  - Browning Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Hoyle Carpenter, The Swan and Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Paul Celan Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Dishman - de Jong Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Albert Einstein - Letter, Eulogy by H. Salinger (Box 7)
  - Epstein Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Fitzbauer - Correspondence and Translations (Box 7)
  - Forster (Box 7)
  - Grillparzer Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Grillparzer Radio Talk (Box 7)
  - Hagelstange Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Henisch, Peter - Correspondence and Translations (Box 7)
  - Humboldt Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Lawson Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Paul Link Correspondence (Box 7)
  - D.L. Salinger - Correspondence and Poems (Box 7)
  - Schönriese (Box 7)
  - Richard Seymour Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Spackman Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Adlai Stevenson, Harry Truman, Gerald Ford Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Vollmer Correspondence (Including Re: Salinger's Duke Appointment), 1955 (Box 7)
  - Wakefield Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Weigand Correspondence, 1964-1982 (Box 7)
  - Donald Yates Correspondence (Box 7)
  - Holiday Cards, 1963-1980 (Box 8)
  - German State Theater Program, 1936 (Box 8)
  - Speech to Angier B. Duke Candidates, 1969 (Box 8)
  - German Embassy Press Kit, 1959 (Box 8)